Inventory of the William B. Terrell Collection, 1900s - 1980s Mss.Coll.015
Belk Library Archives and Special Collections Elon University
William B. Terrell Collection, 1900s - 1980s
Elon University. Belk Library Archives and Special Collections
William B. Terrell
Mss.Coll.015
0.5 1
This small collection reflects William Brown Terrell's lifelong interest in Elon College affairs, particularly documenting his active participation during his student years and his involvement with the Alumni Association. Although some of the items-mainly photographs-represent the years that W. B. Terrell studied at Elon College in the 1920s, the majority of materials reflect his interest in the college generally, spanning the years from the 1900s into the 1980s. The collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material into four series, then chronologically, if applicable. These series are: Books; Literary Productions; Photographs; and Printed Materials.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Gift or Purchase Note
Gift. Please refer to the Correspondence Legal file for more information.
Accession Information
#2006.08.1
Biographical Note
Early Years:
* Born April 15, 1896 in Burlington, NC (source: Social Security Death Index, William B. Terrell Biographical Vertical File)
* Served in WWI, Headquarters Company 120th Infantry, Old Hickory 30th Division. Served in France and Belgium, attaining rank of corporal, before attending Elon College under special arrangements for veterans
* Parents: Bedford Brown Terrell and Jennie Viola Scott Terrell
* Four brothers: James (Jim), Hubert, Ben, and John; two sisters: Blanche and Ida
Education:
* Burlington High School, Alamance County, NC
* Elon College, 1921-1925, received A.B. degree, magna cum laude
* Graduate studies at University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
Elon College Activities:
* Booster's Entertainment Club, 1925
* Burlington Club President, 1923
* Christian Endeavor, Division Leader, 1923
* Class teams in basketball and baseball
* College band
* Commencement marshal
* Democratic Club President, 1925
* Kappa Psi Nu Fraternity
* Managing editor of Maroon and Gold, 1924, and editor, 1925
* Philologian Literary Society
* President of junior class, 1924
* Religious Activities Cabinet, 1922
* Religious Activities Organization, President, 1925
* Secretary of Ministerial Association, 1924
* Student Senate, 1923
* Student Sunday school teacher, 1924
* Treasurer of sophomore class
* Varsity and class track teams
* Vice president of the North Carolina Press Association, 1925
Family:
* Married Katherine Doris McLean of Gibsonville, NC on July 13, 1925
* Katherine Doris McLean was a graduate of Elon, receiving her A.B. degree in 1925 (same graduating class as W. B. Terrell; her photograph is next to Terrell in Phi Psi Cli 1925, senior class); daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Marshall R. McLean
* Doris was on the faculty at Elon College Elementary School for two years. She passed away at the age of 35 on February 26, 1940, after a two-month illness
* They had one son, William Brown Terrell Jr. "Billy", born 1927
* Billy graduated from Elon College High School in 1943, and attended North Carolina State College before appointment to West Point. He graduated from the U.S. Military Academy at West Point in 1949, and received a M.S. degree in astronautics from University of Michigan in 1962
* Billy married Jo Ann Ruth on July 10, 1951. They had one son, William Douglas Terrell, born September 26, 1952, as well as two daughters
* Billy was a pilot in the USAF; decorated for action in Vietnam, 1970
* William B. Terrell married a second time, to Evelyn Mae Rives of Greensboro on May 17, 1947
* Evelyn Mae was a graduate of Woman's College of the University of North Carolina and a teacher in Alamance and Guilford County schools
* They had one son, Charles Bedford Terrell, born 1950
* Charles attended Davidson College in Davidson, NC, and Duke Divinity School in Durham, NC
* Charles married Diana Durig of New Martinsville, WV, on August 23, 1974. They had one son, Robert Bedford Terrell, born February 24, 1977
* Charles became an ordained minister of the Christian Church (Ministry?), May 1975
Career:
* Entered teaching profession following graduation from Elon College, 1925
* English teacher and principal at Tryon High School in Gaston County, NC, for three years, 1925-1928 [Magazine of Elon, November 1976, Alumni News, October 1956, and biographical vertical file]
* Principal of Elon College High School for fifteen years, 1928-1943
* Principal of Wadesboro High School, 1943-1945
* Superintendent of Wadesboro City Schools, 1945-1948
* Superintendent of Warren County Schools, 1948-1957
* Magistrate of the Court, 5th Judicial District, Burlington, NC, 1968-1976, including three years as judge of small-claims court in Alamance County
Organizational Affiliations:
* Board member at Wesley Memorial Methodist Church
* Associate lay leader of the Raleigh District of the Methodist Church
* Masonic order; American Legion; Sudan Temple of the Shrine at New Bern
* Burlington Rotary Club
* Executive Committee member, Occoneechee Council of the Boy Scouts of America
* Secretary of the Warren County Tuberculosis and Health Association
* Director of alumni affairs for thirteen years, 1957-1970 [Magazine of Elon, 1976]
* President of Elon College General Alumni Association, 1952-1954
* Executive Secretary of Elon College General Alumni Association, 1957-1968
* Elon Alumni News editor
Awards:
* Silver Beaver Award of the Boy Scouts of America for volunteer service
* Elon College Alumni Achievement Award, May 28, 1966
* The 1967 edition of Phi Psi Cli was dedicated to Terrell "in appreciation of his unselfish service to Elon College and for his interest in each of her students as individuals"
* Appointed Special Ambassador by Dr. J. E. Danieley, and presented with trip to Europe, Elon College Alumni Tour 1970, in appreciation of services as Alumni Director
* Burlington Police Department Award, plaque commemorating his service as magistrate
* Paul Harris Fellow Award, Burlington Rotary Club, 1988
* Outstanding Citizen award for May 1990, presented by Mayor Jerry R. Tolley
* William B. Terrell Athletic Scholarship, established by students at the former Elon High School, in 1976
Later Years:
* Died December 8, 1991
Biographical Sources:
Newspapers:
Christian Sun
* July 9, 1925, pg. 2
* December 11, 1956, pg. 13
Daily Times-News (Burlington, NC)
* January 19, 1923 (last page)
* September 18, 1928
* August 18, 1943, pg. 6
* February 26, 1940, pg. 12
* February 28, 1940, pg. 12
* March 15, 1947, pg. 5
* May 19, 1947, pg. 8
* October 12, 1948, pg. 5
* November 13, 1948, pg. 12
* July 19, 1951, pg. 8A
* January 4, 1957, pg. 1B, 6B
* June 3, 1967, pg. 4B
* May 17, 1968, pg. 1B
* July 27, 1968, pg. 1B
* July 17, 1970, pg. 5B
* August 24, 1974, pg. 5A
* May 15, 1975, pg. 13B
* November 1, 1976, pg. 3A
* November 9, 1976, pg. 10A
* January 1, 1977, pg. 13A
Maroon and Gold
* September 30, 1925, pg. 3
* September 13, 1928, pg. 3
* October 24, 1956, pg. 1
Magazines:
Elon Alumni News
* October 1948, pg. 8
* May 1953, pg. 6
* October 1956, pg. 2
* July 1966, pg. 11
* July 1967, pg. 5
* May 1968, pg. 23
* April 1969, pg. 32
* July 1970, pg. 2
Magazine of Elon
* November 1976, pg. 7
Books:
* Phi Psi Cli, 1922-1925
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains items primarily about Elon College spanning a broad range of years, from the 1900s to the 1980s. The collection contains some items, mainly photographs, from the years the William Brown Terrell attended Elon College; however, it mainly reflects Mr. Terrell's lifelong interest in Elon College affairs, particularly his involvement with the Alumni Association. The collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material into four series, then chronologically where applicable. These series are: Books; Literary Productions; Photographs; and Printed Materials.
The smallest series, Literary Productions, contains two essays (2:1). One of these essays was written by historian Durward T. Stokes, author of Elon College: Its History and Traditions. This essay provides a historical account of Brick Church, in Guilford County, from its origins in the 1770s until the early 1980s, when the essay is likely to have been written. The other document describes the kidnapping of Elon College alumna Maedell Lambeth, in 1934. This essay has neither author nor date attached, but is likely to have been penned in the early 1980s as well, judging by the story's references.
The largest series is Photographs, containing sixteen black-and-white images of Elon College people and buildings. The majority of these photographs are from the 1920s, including one image of Old Main burning in 1923 (3:1). There are two class photographs-Freshman Class, 1901-02 and Sophomore Class, 1905 (3:2)-as well as the Burlington Club, 1923 (3:1.1), of which W. B. Terrell was president. There are a few undated images (3:3), some of which also appear to have been taken in the 1920s. Several of the photographs in this collection can be found in different issues of the yearbook Phi Psi Cli, in other manuscript collections, or in the Elon Archives' Photograph Collection.
The Books series includes Elon College publications dating from 1912 to 1919 (1:1), before W. B. Terrell was a student. There are five Elon College Bulletins, each being unique issues that do not follow the traditional college catalogue format that the majority of Elon College Bulletins adhere to. These issues are titled Special Funds Number, 1912; Opening Number, 1913; Vacation Number, 1913; Mid-Vacation Number, 1916; and Special Christian Education Number, 1919. Each of these bulletins contains speeches and sermons presented to students, as well as some photographs. The two remaining items in this series are duplicate copies of the 1915 yearbook, Phi Psi Cli (1:2).
The final series, Printed Material, primarily contains newspaper articles about Elon College. The majority of these articles highlight events dating between the mid-1960s and mid-1970s. One news item is about the hiring of L. H. (Hap) Perry as the football head coach in 1946 (4:3); another discusses music professor Malvin N. Artley's violin repair workshop (4:2). The remaining news articles are about Elon College president James Earl Danieley's retirement in 1973 and the donation of the Bob Crumpton Home to Elon College in 1974 (4:4). The most unique item in this series is the Souvenir Library Bulletin, 1924, dedicated to the opening of the Carlton Library. This special bulletin contains photographs of the Carlton family, the dedication speech presented by Louis R. Wilson, and a brief history of the library's establishment (4:1).
Arrangement
This small collection reflects William Brown Terrell's lifelong interest in Elon College affairs, particularly documenting his active participation during his student years and his involvement with the Alumni Association. Although some of the items-mainly photographs-represent the years that W. B. Terrell studied at Elon College in the 1920s, the majority of materials reflect his interest in the college generally, spanning the years from the 1900s into the 1980s. The collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material into four series, then chronologically, if applicable. These series are: Books; Literary Productions; Photographs; and Printed Materials.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Elon College
Elon College Alumni Association
Elon College (N.C.)
Terrell, William Brown, 1896-1991
Elon University -- Archival resources
Related Material
Please consult with the Archivist and Special Collections Librarian for additional information about related materials to this collection.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- 1. Books. 1912-1919., 2 Folders. 7 Items.
  This series, Books, contains Elon College publications in the form of bulletins and yearbooks. There are five bulletins (Special Funds Number, 1912; Opening Number, 1913; Vacation Number, 1913; Mid-Vacation Number, 1916; and Special Christian Education Number, 1919), as well as two copies of the 1915 yearbook, Phi Psi Cli. These publications describe the religious, academic, political, and social life at Elon College during those years. The bulletins are unique issues that do not follow the form of the traditional college catalogue. The Special Funds Number of March 1912 lists financial contributions to the college, while the remaining issues contain addresses, sermons, and speeches presented to students, as well as photographs of the college and its students. The yearbook highlights student life, including organizational and athletic activities, and provides photographs of students, faculty, and staff. Some of these items are stored offsite; however, where this is the case, a "public use" copy is available in the Archives room in the library.
  - Folder 1. Bulletin of Elon College. 1912-1919.
  - Folder 2. Yearbook. 1915.
    - * Phi Psi Cli
    - * Elon College
- 2. Literary Productions. No Date., 1 Folder. 2 Items.
  The Literary Productions series is the smallest in the collection, containing only two essays. One essay is titled "History of Brick Church," and was written by historian Durward T. Stokes, alumnus, emeritus professor of history, and author of Elon College: Its History and Traditions. The essay traces the history of one Guilford County church from its origins in the 1770s to 1981. The essay is undated but is likely from early 1980s. The second essay, "Elon Co-ed Kidnapped," bears neither author nor date; but is likely to have been written after 1980, based on its references. This essay describes the holdup of a Burlington Mills office and the kidnapping of Elon alumna Maedell Lambeth and her coworker, Miss Eckner, in August 1934.
  - Folder 1. Essays. No Date.
    - * Elon College, NC
    - * Elon College
    - * Lambeth, Maedell
    - * "Elon Co-Ed Kidnapped"
    - * Stokes, Durward T. (author)
    - * "History of Brick Church"
    - * Guilford County, NC
    - * Orange County, NC
- 3. Photographs. 1900-1920s and No Date., 4 Folders. 16 Items.
  The largest series in the collection, Photographs, contains images documenting Elon College, primarily in the 1920s during the years that William B. Terrell attended. There are exterior images of various buildings, including one of the Old Main administrative building burning during the fire of 1923. This photograph is printed in the yearbook Phi Psi Cli of that year. There is one 1926 image of the interior of Whitley Auditorium which captures Rev. James W. "Uncle" Wellons preaching on his 100th birthday. [This photograph, and further details of this event, can also be found in the James Willis Wellons Collection, Mss.Coll.#006.] Several of the photographs document Elon College students; specifically, there are two class photographs from 1901 and 1905 and one of the Burlington Club of 1923, of which W. B. Terrell was president. Also included are several unidentified group photographs and an assortment of images depicting Elon students.
  - Folder 1. Buildings. Elon College. 1920s.
    - * West Dorm
    - * Administrative Building, Old Main
    - * Fires-Old Main-photo in Phi Psi Cli 1923, page 10
    - * Ladies Cooperative Hall
    - * Whitley Auditorium, January 1926
    - * Harper, William Allen, January 1926
    - * Staley, William W., January 1926
    - * Wellons, James W. "Uncle", January 1926
  - Folder 1.1. Burlington Club. Elon College. 1923.
    - * W.B. Terrell, Burlington Club President
    - * Phi Psi Cli 1923, page 183
    - * Barber, J. D.
    - * Combs, A. L.
    - * Cude, E. F.
    - * Elder, W. C.
    - * Fix, J. M.
    - * King, O. H.
    - * Gibbs, F. Lee
    - * Goins, J. A.
    - * Isley, H. L.
    - * Isley, C. G.
    - * James, L. G.
    - * Paschall, Annie
    - * Somers, C. L.
    - * Terrell, W. B.
    - * Loy, R. T.
    - * Morrow, Eunice
    - * Loy, Kittie
    - * Jones, M. L.
    - * Garrison, C. M.
    - * Simpson, J. V.
    - * McPherson, H. E.
    - * Elder, Fannie Glenn
    - * Miles, Shellie
    - * Homewood, Louise
    - * Horne, Lillie
    - * Horne, Lillian
    - * Isley, Bertha
  - Folder 2. Classes of Elon College. 1900-1909.
    - * Freshman Class, 1901-1902
    - * Sophomore Class, 1905
    - * Iseley, Bertha
    - * Eldridge, Lucy
    - * Holland, Susie
    - * Pitt, Mary Lou
    - * Ames, Willie
    - * Holland, Goldie
    - * Holleman, Martha Pearl
    - * Holland, Sadie
    - * Pritchard, Mary
    - * Taylor, Maude
    - * Kernodle, Annie
    - * Herndon, Gertrude
    - * Shoffner, Maggie
    - * Kernodle, Iola
    - * Turner, Olive
    - * Moffitt, Clara
    - * Brunk, Ella
    - * Lincoln, Lucius
    - * Pritchette, Virgil
    - * Talton, Lucy
    - * Jones, Tom
    - * Neville, J. B.
    - * Holland, Harvey
    - * Norfleet, John
    - * Holland, Pretlow
    - * Banks, F. T.
    - * Long, J. Dolph
    - * Holmes, Howard Braxton, Professor
    - * Andes, A. W.
    - * Wills, Euclid
    - * Holland, Charles E.
    - * Kernodle, June
    - * Gay, Leland
    - * Harden, Ann
    - * Newman, Alma
    - * Franks, Lenora
    - * Whitley, Homer
    - * Godwin, Jennie
    - * East, Eileen
    - * Pritchard, Josaphene
    - * Colley, J. C.
    - * Wilkins, J. C.
    - * Pritchette, C. E.
    - * Lankford, C. O.
  - Folder 3. Miscellaneous. No Date.
    - * Athletics, Elon College
    - * Students, Elon College
- 4. Printed Material. Inclusive: 1924-1974. Bulk: 1960s-1970s., 4 Folders. 7 Items.
  This series, Printed Material, is predominantly comprised of newspaper articles, the majority of which date approximately from the mid-1960s to the mid-1970s.
  The most unique item is the Souvenir Library Bulletin, a 1924 bulletin of Elon College dedicated to the opening of the Carlton Library. This booklet describes the events leading up to the need for a new library and the dedication of the building, and also gives a detailed description of the library. The full text of the dedication speech titled "The Place of the Library in College Life," given by Louis R. Wilson, Librarian of the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, is included. Photographs of the new library and members of the Carlton family are interspersed throughout the bulletin as well.
  The remaining items document events at Elon College. One 1946 news item announces L. J. (Hap) Perry as the new football head coach. A second article (undated, ca. 1966-1971) describes the violin repair workshop of music professor Malvin N. Artley. Two items document Dr. James Earl Danieley's retirement as Elon College's president in 1973. The remaining two articles announce the gift of the Crumpton House, located in Person County, NC, to Elon College in 1974. These articles describe the history of the property and announce plans for its use as the Crumpton Conference Center. Further details about the Crumpton Conference Center can be found in the "Crumpton House" campus buildings vertical file in the Archives room in the Library.
  - Folder 1. Booklets. 1924.
    - * Souvenir Library Bulletin
    - * Elon College, NC
    - * Carlton Library Building
    - * Wilson, Louis Round
  - Folder 2. Newspaper Clippings. No Date.
    - * Artley, Dr. Malvin N., ca. 1966-1971? (Music Professor at Elon College, 1965-2004)
    - * Violin repairs
    - * Dunn, Mamie
  - Folder 3. Newspaper Clippings. 1946.
    - * Perry, L. J. (Hap)
    - * Athletic Director, Elon College
    - * Football
    - * Reidsville, NC
    - * Smith, Leon Edgar
  - Folder 4. Newspaper Clippings. 1970s.
    - * Crumpton, Dr. John L.
    - * Crumpton Conference Center
    - * Crumpton, Preto Brown
    - * Crumpton, Pretto Browne
    - * Crumpton House
    - * Crumpton Homestead
    - * Elon College alumni
    - * Danieley, Dr. James Earl-retirement
    - * Elon College president, 1957-1973
    - * Daily Times-News, Burlington, NC
    - * Danieley, Mark
    - * Danieley, Jane Elizabeth
    - * Danieley, Ned
    - * Danieley, Verona Daniels